<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?> 
<welcomePage title="PMD For Eclipse">
	<intro>
	This page will help familiarize you with the Eclipse PMD development tooling.
	To get started, read the sections below and click on the related links.
	</intro>

	<item><b>Introduction to PMD</b>
	PMD is a tool intended to check the semantic of Java code. It helps developer to
	build better code by alerting on bad constructs. Unlike other tools, PMD doesn't
	check style, ie. naming, spaces, or javadoc, but deals only with syntax.
	To learn more about PMD check <topic id="/net.sourceforge.pmd.eclipse.core/toc.xml">PMD	documentation</topic>.
	</item>
	
	<item><b>Running PMD automatically or manually</b>
	PMD can be launched either manually on a selection of files, folders or projects
	or can be run automatically each time a file is changed or added to a project.
	To let PMD running automatically, simply check the box in the project PMD property
	page. To run PMD manually, select the menu item in the contextual menu of your
	selection.
	</item>
	
	<item><b>Viewing PMD violations</b>
	Basically PMD violations are problem markers and appear in the Tasks view (Eclipse v2)
	or Problems view (Eclipse v3). The plugin provides also a dedicated view for violations
	that provides more informations. To show the violation views, select it in the
	Show View dialog.
	</item>
	
	<item><b>Detect suspect cut and paste code</b>
	PMD comes with tool that enable you to detect duplicate code. Select a project 
	and select PMD-&gt;Find Suspect Cut And Paste in the context menu.
	</item>
	
	<item><b>Configuring the plugin</b>
	PMD is configured <i>via</i> the Eclipse preferences feature. Open the preferences
	dialog and select the PMD preference page. Three pages let you configure PMD and
	the Cut and Paste Detector and import, export and configure rules.
	</item>
	
	<item><b>Configuring a project</b>
	PMD can also be configured on a per project basis. Edit a project properties dialog
	and the select the PMD property page. This page lets you enable PMD to run automatically
	for this project, select a subset of the configured rules, specify a file filer
	(working set) or tell PMD to use a ruleset that comes with the project instead of
	the plugin configured rules.
	</item>
	
	<item><b>Quickfixes</b>
	This version of the plugin comes with a preview of the future quicfix feature. This
	feature is currently implemented only for the "Duplicate Imports" rule and propose
	to simply delete the line where the violation occurs.
	</item>

	<item><b>To learn more</b>
	Check the <topic id="/net.sourceforge.pmd.eclipse.core/toc.xml">how to... section</topic> of the online help to learn more about the plugin.
	</item>

</welcomePage>
