<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="tom@infoether.org">Pieter Vanraemdonck</author>
    <title>JSP Support Notes</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
<section name="Documentation of JSP support in PMD">
    <subsection name="What is currently supported and what is not">
    <p>In short, JSP files that are XHTML-compliant, are supported.
    Except for files that contain inline DTDs; only references to external
    DTD files are supported (having inline DTD will result in a parsing
    error).</p>
    <p>The XHTML support means that:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>opening tags must be accompanied by corresponding <span style="text-decoration: underline;">closing tags</span>
    (or they must be empty tags). This means that currently a "&lt;HR&gt;"
    tag without corresponding closing tag will result in a parsing error.</li>
    <li><span style="text-decoration: underline;">attribute values</span> must be <span style="text-decoration: underline;">surrounded by</span> single or double <span style="text-decoration: underline;">quotes</span>. This means that the following syntax will result in a parsing error:<br />
    &lt;MyTag myAttr1=true myAttr2=1024/&gt;</li>
    <li>&lt; and &gt; characters must be <span style="text-decoration: underline;">escaped</span>, or put inside a CDATA section.</li>
    <p>PMD creates a "Abstract Syntax Tree" representation of source code; the rules use such a tree as input.
    For JSP files, the following constructs are parsed into nodes of the tree:</p>
    <ul>
    <li>XML-elements, XML-attributes, XML-comments, doctype-declarations, CDATA,</li>
    <li>JSP-directives, JSP-declarations, JSP-comments, JSP-scriptlets, JSP-expressions, Expression Language expressions, JSF value bindings</li>
    <li>everything else is seen as flat text nodes.</li>
    </ul>
    <li>Java code (e.g. in JSP-scriptlets) and EL expressions are not parsed or
    further broken down. If you want to create rules that check the code
    inside EL expressions or JSP scriptlets (a.o.), you currently would
    have to do "manual" string manipulation (e.g. using regular
    expressions).</li>
    </ul>
    </subsection>
    <subsection name="How to use it">
    <p>Using the command-line interface, two new options can be used in the arguments string:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>"-jsp" : this triggers checking JSP files (they are not checked by default)</li>
        <li>"-nojava" : this tells PMD not to check java source files (they are checked by default)</li>
    </ul>
    <p>Using the Ant task, you decide if PMD must check JSP files by choosing
    what files are given to the PMD task. If you use a fileset that
    contains only ".java" files, JSP files obviously will not be checked.</p>
    <p>If you want to call the PMD API for checking JSP files, you should investigate the javadoc of PMD.</p>
    </subsection>
</section>
  </body>
</document>
