<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="tom@infoether.com">Tom Copeland</author>
    <title>Finding copied and pasted code</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
   <section name="Copied and pasted code is usually bad">
     <p>But it can be hard to find, especially in a large project.  So we wrote a utility - CPD - to find it for us.
         It's been through three major incarnations:</p>
         <ul>
             <li>First we wrote it using a variant of Michael Wise's Greedy String Tiling algorithm (our variant is described
         <a href="http://www.onjava.com/pub/a/onjava/2003/03/12/pmd_cpd.html">here</a>)</li>
             <li>Then it was completely
         rewritten by Brian Ewins using the
         <a href="http://dogma.net/markn/articles/bwt/bwt.htm">Burrows-Wheeler transform</a></li>
             <li>Finally, it was rewritten by Steve Hawkins to use the
         <a href="http://www.nist.gov/dads/HTML/karpRabin.html">Karp-Rabin</a> string matching algorithm.</li>
         </ul>
          <p>Each rewrite made it much faster, and now it can process the JDK java.* packages in about 4 seconds (on my Linux workstation, at least).</p>
     <p>Here's a <a href="images/screenshot_cpd.png">screenshot</a> of CPD after running on the JDK java.lang package.</p>
     <p>Note that CPD works with Java, C, C++, and PHP code.</p>
     <p>If you have <a href="http://java.sun.com/products/javawebstart/">Java Web Start</a>, you can <a href="cpd.jnlp">run CPD by clicking  here</a>.</p>
     <p><a href="cpdresults.txt">Here</a> are the duplicates CPD found in the JDK 1.4 source code.</p>
     <p><a href="cpp_cpdresults.txt">Here</a> are the duplicates CPD found in the APACHE_2_0_BRANCH branch of Apache
         (just the <code>httpd-2.0/server/</code> directory).</p>
       <p>Andy Glover wrote an Ant task for CPD; here's how to use it:</p>
       <source>
<![CDATA[
<target name="cpd">
    <taskdef name="cpd" classname="net.sourceforge.pmd.cpd.CPDTask" />
    <cpd minimumTokenCount="100" outputFile="/home/tom/cpd.txt">
        <fileset dir="/home/tom/tmp/ant">
            <include name="**/*.java"/>
        </fileset>
    </cpd>
</target>
]]>
       </source>
       <p>Also, you can get verbose output from this task by running ant with the <code>-v</code> flag; i.e., <code>ant -v -f mybuildfile.xml cpd</code>.</p>
       <p>There's also a JavaSpaces version available for splitting the CPD effort across a farm of machines.
       I usually post news on that <a href="http://cpd.jini.org/">here</a> and the releases are <a href="http://sf.net/projects/pmd/">here</a>.
           This project is pretty much dead, though, since the current code is  fast enough to just run it on one machine.</p>
     <p>Suggestions?  Comments?  Post them <a href="http://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?forum_id=188192">here</a>.  Thanks!</p>
   </section>
  </body>
</document>


