<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="tom@infoether.org">Tom Copeland</author>
    <title>Credits</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Credits">
        <subsection name="Committers">
        <ul>
            <li>David Dixon-Peugh - much of the early work on the grammar, initial Emacs plugin</li>
            <li>David Craine - JBuilder plugin</li>
            <li>Philippe Herlin - Eclipse plugin, fixed bugs in RuleSetFactory</li>
            <li>Tom Copeland - lead developer, JDeveloper plugin, Gel plugin, initial jEdit plugin, IDEAJ integration</li>
            <li>Jiger Patel - jEdit plugin</li>
            <li>Gunnlaugur Thor Briem - NetBeans plugin, Maven build script fixes, bug report on JavaCC parser's use of java.lang.Error</li>
            <li>Ole-Martin Mork - NetBeans plugin</li>
        </ul>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Committers emeritus">
        <ul>
            <li>Don Leckie - The PMD GUI</li>
            <li>Tom Burke - Eclipse plugin</li>
            <li>Rich Kilmer - logo design</li>
            <li>Nascif Abousalh Neto - Emacs plugin</li>
            <li>Paul Kendall - various bugfixes and features</li>
            <li>Alex Chaffee - various bugfixes and features</li>
            <li>Siegfried Goeschl - original Maven plugin, various bugfixes and features</li>
        </ul>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Significant contributors">
        <ul>
            <li>Brian Ewins - complete rewrite of CPD based on the Burrows-Wheeler transform</li>
            <li>Dan Sheppard - XPath engine integration concept and implementation</li>
            <li>Steve Hawkins - rewrite of CPD based on Karp-Rabin string matching</li>
        </ul>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Contributors">
        <ul>
            <li>Radim Kubacki - OptimizableToArrayCallRule suggestion, bug reports, pmd-netbeans feedback</li>
            <li>Will Sargent - AvoidThrowingCertainExceptionTypesRule, AvoidCatchingNPERule, ExceptionAsFlowControlRule, URL updates for 'Similar projects' page</li>
            <li>Mike Thome - BadComparisonRule suggestion</li>
            <li>Bertrand Mollinier Toublet - Bug report which led to platform character set encoding enhancement</li>
            <li>Choi Ki Soo - Found bug in XMLRenderer</li>
            <li>wedemann - Found bug in RuleSetFactory XPath message variable plugging</li>
            <li>Lori Olson - Found copy/paste bug in rule descriptions</li>
            <li>Adrian Papari - Wrote the PapariTextRenderer</li>
            <li>Curt Cox - some additions to the 'Similar Projects' page</li>
            <li>Michael Griffel - bug fix for XMLRenderer</li>
            <li>Doug Tillman - correction to finalizers.xml examples</li>
            <li>Luis Alberto Domínguez Ruiz - bug report for IfElseStmtsMustUseBracesRule</li>
            <li>Chad Loder - SuspiciousOctalEscapeRule, EmptyStatementNotInLoop, SuspiciousHashcodeMethodName, NonCaseLabelInSwitchStatement, DefaultLabelNotLastInSwitchStmt, NonStaticInitializer, ExplicitCallToFinalize, MethodWithSameNameAsEnclosingClassRuleTest, FinalizeDoesNotCallSuperFinalize, FinalizeOverloaded, FinalizeOnlyCallsSuperFinalize, UnconditionalIfStatement, AvoidDollarSigns, EmptyStaticInitializer, EmptyFinalizerMethod rule, DontImportSun rule, improvements to ASTBooleanLiteral</li>
            <li>Maik Schreiber - AccessNode bug report, other bug reports</li>
            <li>Lokesh Gupta - improvements to the AST viewer</li>
            <li>Jesse Glick - improvements to VariableNamingConventionsRule, patch for UnusedModifierRule, bug fix for VariableNameDeclarations rule, an excellent discussion on the UnnecessaryConstructorRule</li>
            <li>Nicolas Liochon - CloneShouldCallSuperCloneRule implementation</li>
            <li>Philippe Couton - OverrideBothEqualsAndHashcodeRule bug report, UseSingletonRule improvements, JUnitStaticSuiteRule improvements</li>
            <li>Brandon Franklin - many pmd-web ideas</li>
            <li>Slava Pestov -  Suggestions for jEdit plugin enhancements.</li>
            <li>Andriy Rozeluk - Suggestions for improving UnnecessaryReturn, AvoidDuplicateLiterals RFEs and bug reports, various other RFEs and thoughtful discussions as well</li>
            <li>Olivier Mengué - Diagnosed and patched XML report character encoding problems</li>
            <li>Hariolf Häfele - PMD-JDeveloper plugin bug reports</li>
            <li>Pieter Bloemendaal - AvoidReassigningParametersRule bug report</li>
            <li>Vladimir Bossicard - suggested AbstractNamingRule, test package organization suggestions, VBHTMLRenderer, numerous feature requests and bug reports, several rule suggestions derived from <a href="http://junit-addons.sf.net/">JUnit-Addons</a>, evangelism :-)</li>
            <li>Ken Foskey - noticed bad link</li>
            <li>Stephan Janssen - promoted PMD for <a href="https://jjguidelines.dev.java.net/">JJGuidelines</a></li>
            <li>Ron Sidi - bug reports</li>
            <li>David Koontz - suggestions for tweaking PMD command line options</li>
            <li>Jeff Epstein - TextPad integration and tests</li>
            <li>Gabe Johnson - CloseConnectionRule</li>
            <li>Roelof Vuurboom - posted report of QStudio analysis of PMD</li>
            <li>Jeff Anderson - node finding utility code</li>
            <li>Boris Gruschko - regression test suites, nifty AST/XPath viewer</li>
            <li>Trevor Harmon - rewrote XSLT script</li>
            <li>Vadim Nasardinov - xdocs cleanup, run.sh cleanup</li>
            <li>Sreenivasa Viswanadha - grammar cleanup for Ctrl-Z problem</li>
            <li>Sigiswald Madou - bug report</li>
            <li>Dan Tullis - bug report</li>
            <li>George Menhorn - CPD bug reports and suggestions</li>
            <li>Paul Roebuck - Ant build improvement, several bug reports</li>
            <li>Jon A. Maxwell - Bug report</li>
            <li>Erik Lee - Bug report</li>
            <li>Joerg K. Wegner - pmd-web suggestions</li>
            <li>Chris Webster - fix (and test) for UnnecessaryConstructorRule, BooleanInstantiation rule</li>
            <li>Colin Simmonds - detailed bug reports</li>
            <li>Trond Andersen - AvoidCatchingThrowable, ExceptionSignatureDeclaration, ExceptionTypeChecking</li>
            <li>Bernd Jansen - grammer modification</li>
            <li>Jarle Naess - bug report</li>
            <li>Jeff Anderson - VariableNamingConventionsRule, MethodNamingConventionsRule, ClassNamingConventionsRule</li>
            <li>Frank van Puffelen - documentation suggestions</li>
            <li>Conrad Roche - bug report</li>
            <li>mcclain looney - patch for CPD GUI, bug reports</li>
            <li>Ralf Hauser - Various documentation suggestions, cygwin-run.sh</li>
            <li>Pablo Casado - Bug report for UseSingletonRule</li>
            <li>Nicolai Czempin - Various rule suggestions, additional PMD backronyms</li>
            <li>Frank Hardisty - BeanMembersShouldSerializeRule</li>
            <li>Randall Schulz - bug report for LooseCouplingRule</li>
            <li>Wim Bervoets - bug report for the PMD Ant task</li>
            <li>Niels Peter Strandberg - various tweaks to the PMD Swing UI</li>
            <li>Ian Shef - documentation updates, bug reports on the Gel IDE plugin</li>
            <li>Astro Jetson Jr - a tweak for the ShortVariableNameRule</li>
            <li>Paul King - a complete rewrite of the Gel plugin</li>
            <li>Gael Marziou - "exclude" rule feature request, bug reports</li>
            <li>Philippe T'Seyen - refactoring and cleanup of the CPD Ant task, an XML renderer (with unit tests!) for CPD</li>
            <li>Michael Montuori - bug reports on the Gel IDE plugin</li>
            <li>Michael Hosier - bug reports on the Gel IDE plugin</li>
            <li>Matthew Harrah - script bug report</li>
            <li>Richard Jenson - CPD on Win32 troubleshooting</li>
            <li>Daniel Bruguier - CPD on Win32 troubleshooting</li>
            <li>Mario Claerhout - CPD optimizations and suggestions</li>
            <li>Sameer Nanda - CPD Ant task bug report</li>
            <li>Nanne Baars - grammar suggestions, rule suggestions</li>
            <li>Adam Nemeth - bug fixes for UnnecessaryConstructorRule</li>
            <li>Andrew Glover - the CPDTask, ExcessivePublicCountRule, CouplingBetweenObjectsRule, ExcessiveImportsRule, documentation tweaks</li>
            <li>Robert Leland - bug report</li>
            <li>Carl Gilbert - AccessorClassGenerationRule, DoubleCheckedLockingRule, ConstructorCallsOverridableMethodRule, bug reports, feature requests, and documentation improvements</li>
            <li>Dave Fuller - improved resource loading code (packaged in a nice diff, too!)</li>
            <li>David Whitmore - parser bug report</li>
            <li>David Campbell - detailed bugs reports, Ant task refactoring, documentation tweaks</li>
            <li>Michael Sutherland - bug report in IfStmtMustUseBracesRule</li>
            <li>Egon Willighagen - pmd-web suggestion</li>
            <li>Didier Duquennoy - pmd-netbeans feedback</li>
            <li>Adam Nemeth - bug report on missing final attribute for local variable declarations</li>
            <li>Frederic Harper - bug report and subsequent troubleshooting</li>
            <li>Mats Henricson - an XSLT script and several bug reports</li>
            <li>Luke Francl - numerous <b>high quality</b> feature suggestions and bug reports</li>
            <li>Martin Cooper - feature suggestions</li>
            <li>Bruce Mayhew - feedback on the jEdit plugin</li>
            <li>Juergen Ebert - feature suggestions and pmd-netbeans feedback</li>
            <li>J.D. Fagan - feature suggestions</li>
            <li>William McArthur - ForLoopShouldBeWhileLoop rule</li>
            <li>Ales Bukovsky - pmd-netbeans feedback</li>
            <li>Stefan Bodewig - bug report</li>
            <li>Paul Kendall - enhanced EmptyCatchBlock rule</li>
            <li>Sean Sullivan - rule suggestions</li>
            <li>Dale Vissar - rule suggestions</li>
            <li>Alina Copeland - pmd-web formulas, pmd-dcpd optimizations</li>
            <li>Vincent Massol - bug reports, design suggestions, feature suggestions, Maven guidance</li>
            <li>Peter Donald - design suggestions</li>
            <li>Liam Holohan - bug reports</li>
            <li>Ralph Schaer - bug reports and verification</li>
            <li>Damian O'Neill - Ant task patches</li>
        </ul>
        </subsection>
        <subsection name="Organizations">
        <table>
          <tr><td><center><img src="images/darpa.jpg"/></center></td>
              <td><a href="http://www.darpa.mil/">DARPA</a> for funding
                  the Ultra*Log effort which spawned PMD.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><center><img src="images/ultralog.gif"/></center></td>
              <td><a href="http://www.ultralog.net/">Ultra*Log</a> for
                  letting us build PMD to help the code get better.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><center><img src="images/cougaar.jpg"/></center></td>
              <td><a href="http://www.cougaar.org/">Cougaar</a> is an
                  agent architecture Ultra*Log is based on.  (Which needs
                  quite a bit of PMD also.)</td></tr>
          <tr><td><center><img src="http://sourceforge.net/sflogo.php?group_id=56262"/></center></td>
              <td><a href="http://sourceforge.net/">SourceForge</a> for
                  providing hosting services for PMD.</td></tr>
          <tr><td><center><img src="images/refactorit_logo.gif"/></center></td>
              <td><a href="http://www.refactorit.com/">RefactorIT</a> for letting
                  their software be used free-of-charge on PMD code
                  (<a href="http://www.refactorit.com/index.html?id=649">OpenSource
                  Community License</a>)</td></tr>
            <tr><td><center><img src="images/qasystems_logo.jpg"/></center></td>
                <td><a href="http://www.qa-systems.com/products/qstudioforjava/">QA-Systems</a> for sending in some
                    handy utilities for PMD and shipping PMD inside their QStudio product
                    </td></tr>
        </table>
        </subsection>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
