<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="dpeugh@users.sourceforge.net">David Dixon-Peugh</author>
    <title>IDE Integrations</title>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Integrations with IDEs">
      <subsection name="Summary">
<table>
  <tr><td><b>IDE</b></td>
      <td><b>File Release</b></td>
      <td><b>Current Version</b></td>
      <td><b>Author</b></td>
      <td><b>Download</b></td></tr>
  <tr><td>Eclipse</td>
      <td>pmd-eclipse</td>
      <td>0.1</td>
      <td>dpeugh</td>
      <td><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=56262&amp;release_id=100231">X</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td>Emacs</td>
      <td>pmd-emacs</td>
      <td>0.1</td>
      <td>dpeugh</td>
      <td><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=56262&amp;release_id=99873">X</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td>JBuilder</td>
      <td>pmd-jbuilder</td>
      <td>0.3</td>
      <td>dcraine</td>
      <td><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=56262&amp;release_id=100422">X</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td>JEdit</td>
      <td>pmd-jedit</td>
      <td>0.6</td>
      <td>tomcopeland</td>
      <td><a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=56262&amp;release_id=101841">X</a></td></tr>
  <tr><td>Maven</td>
      <td>pmd-maven</td>
      <td>N/A</td>
      <td>dpeugh</td>
      <td>N/A</td></tr>
  <tr><td>Ant</td>
      <td>N/A</td>
      <td>N/A</td>
      <td>tomcopeland</td>
      <td>N/A</td></tr>
  </table>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Eclipse">
<p>
Integration into Eclipse is accomplished through the extensive
Plugin architecture provided by Eclipse.  It is written in Java,
and has some nice features to it.
</p>
<p>
Eclipse Integration will fill the TODO list of the project with
each Rule Violation that PMD detects.  These violations are marked
in the code with the Task icon on the left hand side of the editor.
p>
<p>
The Eclipse integration was written with the version 2.0 of Eclipse,
so I'm not certain if it will work on earlier versions.
</p>
<p>
As Eclipse is not my primary IDE, we are looking for people who can
make suggestions, and possibly even handle the care and feeding of
the Eclipse plugin.
</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Emacs">
<p>
Integration with GNU Emacs is performed through ELisp. (what else?)
</p>
<p>
There is only one command "pmd-current-buffer" which will execute
PMD on the Java code in the current buffer.  It will generate an
XML report in the *PMD* buffer.
</p>
<p>
It is planned to provide a better format for the results from PMD
to make usage in Emacs better.  Additonally, it is hoped that we
will be able to jump from a rule violation, to the position in the
code which caused it.
</p>

      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Borland JBuilder">
<p>
To enable this OpenTool in JBuilder, place the PMDOpenTool.jar file AND the pmd-x.x.jar file (where
x.x is the version id) into JBuilder's lib/ext directory.  Once JBuilder is restart, the PMD OpenTool
will be enabled.
What you can do:
<ul>
<li>Check a single file by bringing up the context menu from the file tab and selecting PMDCheck</li>
<li>Configure the rulesets that the PMD OpenTool will use by selecting Tools->PMD->Configure PMD</li>
<li>Check all the files in a project by bringing up the context menu for the project node and selecting PMD Check Project</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>When running PMD, the results will be displayed in the MessageView under a tab called PMD Results.  If you click on a
violation message within this view, you will be taken to the line in the source code where the violation was detected.
</p>
<p>Things still to do:
<ul>
<li>Enable selection of individual rules within a rule set (maybe)</li>
<li>Optional insertion of @todo comments at the point of a violation</li>
<li>Possibly provide configurable ability to limit the number of violations per rule per file</li>
</ul>
</p>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="JEdit">
<p>
This is more or less the standard JEdit plugin - doubleclick a directory, select Plugins->PMD->Check current directory and
you get a popup list of problems.  It uses the ErrorList plugin which provides the "jump to the correct line"
and syntax highlighting functionality.  Things to do:</p>
<ul>
<li>Add some stuff to the configuration thing so you can turn on/off individual rules.</li>
<li>Clean up the threading so the GUI doesn't freeze while PMD is working</li>
</ul>

</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Maven">
<p>
The Maven plugin will be written using the new plugin architecture
that is currently being developed by the Maven project.  Currently
we are waiting for the development to settle down before commiting
any serious resources to it.
</p>
<p>
The Maven plugin will work by generating web pages which blend into
the website, identifing Rule Violations.
</p>
<p>
A possible other integration with Maven, will be the integration
of PMD into JXR or LXR.  This should allow annotation of code in
the web environment.  Work on this has not started.
</p>
      </subsection>
      <subsection name="Ant">
<p>
Using PMD with Ant is such a standard usage that we hardly think of it as an integration point.  But, I guess
it is.  You can read more about the PMD Ant task <a href="running.html">here</a>.
</p>
      </subsection>
      </section>
  </body>
</document>
